As soon as you see a problem, what is
the first thing that you do? You look up
a test case and then you decide, okay, I
want to scan all of these elements.
There are multiple ways to do it. You
can either use a two-pointer approach or
you can also use a fast pointer and a
slow pointer. But sometimes there is a
thought that comes to your mind that
okay, I need to remember this element
somehow so I can come at a solution. As
soon as this thought hits your mind, it
means you will either want to use a
hashmap or a hash fet. And that is the
pattern we are going to talk about in
this video. Hello friends, welcome back
to my channel.
First of all, we need to understand what
do you actually mean by a hashmap and a
hash fet. These two are very essential
data structures which are available in
almost every programming language. Yes,
they take up some space, but they give
you a time complexity of order of one
when you have to look up elements. So,
how do they work? For example, this is
how you can imagine a hash set to be. In
a hash set, you can never have any
duplicates. So for example, if I try to
add numbers like two, three and then a
five and then let us say I try to add a
two again. This two will not make an
entry in your hashet because two already
exists. Similarly, you can add more
distinct elements.
It is guaranteed that any time you check
your hash fret all of the elements will
be unique. One more advantage that you
get is you can query all of these
elements in a constant time. For
example, you can immediately ask, hey,
is the number three in my hashet? And
with the order of one-time complexity,
you will either return a true or a
false. If a number does not exist, you
can still ask, hey, is 11 in my hash? It
does not exist. So, you will get a
false. This is the basic idea of a
hashet. Somehow you are trying to
remember okay these are all the unique
elements that I have encountered and it
is not necessary that all of these have
to be integers. They can be strings they
can be also objects. It is up to you to
decide what do you want to do with it.
Similarly you also have the concept of a
hashmap. In a hashmap you will have a
key and a value. But all of these keys
they are guaranteed to be unique. You
can assign different type of keys with
different type of values. For example,
your keys can be all integers and your
values could be string as well. And at
any instant none of these values will be
duplicated. You can have duplicated
values.
This is perfectly fine. But you cannot
have a two over here. This is the
advantage that a hashmap gives you and
once again it will take up a order of n
extra space where n is the number of
elements you are trying to store in your
map. But the advantage you get is you
can query all of these values in a
constant time. So you can straight away
ask okay is two present in my map? So
you will get either a true or a false
and you can ask one more information
what is the value associated with two.
So you will return CD. So we are getting
two advantages over here. You can either
ask in your map is the key present. So
this is very similar to a hash fet but
at the same time you also get to store a
certain value that is associated with
it. This is the basic understanding how
hash maps and hash fetss work. So before
we try to understand even more, let us
quickly take a look at some very
familiar examples and then you will
start to get an idea about it. I'm
pretty sure you must have heard about
this problem to sum but this time your
array is unsorted. The idea over here is
you are given an unsorted array and you
have to tell me if there are any two
inteious available that sum up to a
particular number. Let us say the
desired sum is 10. So how do you
approach it? A brute force way will be
that you will pick up two elements every
time and then try to find out the sum.
This will take up a time complexity of
order of n². But you can do something
efficient. What you can do is you can
pick up a hash set. In this set first of
all add all the numbers that are
available to you. Immediately I can
query if any of this number is present.
So how do you approach it? You take up
this number minus2 and then if you want
to find another number such that -2 + of
x gives you 10. So what should be the
value of x? x should be 12. Correct? If
12 was present in my array then you got
the answer. But how do you scan for 12?
You don't want to iterate over your
array again. This is where this set
comes in. You will immediately look up
is 12 present in my hash fet. No. So it
means 2 cannot be a part of your answer.
What about minus 5? Now you need min -5
+ of 15 to get 10. Correct? So you look
up can you find a 15? No. So this also
cannot be a part of your answer. Can you
use six? To get 10 you will need a four
correct. So you can now search hey is
four present in my hash? Yes you found a
value. So you can say that okay 6a 4 are
the two inteious which will add up to
give you the result 10 n. You can see
how hash set gave us advantage. The time
complexity changed from order of n² to
order of 2n which is relatively just
order of n because you are scanning the
array only twice. But keep in mind that
you used up extra order of n space to
arrive at this efficient solution.
Let us move on to another problem. Now
over here you are given a sudoku board
and you have to verify if this sudoku
board is actually valid or not. If you
remember what are the rules of sudoku.
For each of these small squares you
should have number from 1 to 9.
And for each of these columns you should
also have the number from 1 to 9. And
this should be true for each of the
column. Again all of these rows they
should have numbers from 1 to 9. If any
row or any column or any of the smaller
squares they have duplicate numbers it
is not a valid pseudoku. So what does
this tell you? You have to again think
okay have I encountered this number
before? Is there a duplicate?
Immediately you should use a hash set.
So what are we going to do over here? We
can create individual hashetss for each
of these smaller squares. So you are
going to have nine of these hashetss for
each of the smaller squares. Then you
can have individual hash fetss for each
of your rows. And then similarly you can
have individual hash fats for your
columns also. For each of these hash
fits you will try to add all of the
numbers. So take up your first square
and add all of these numbers. take up
your second square and add all of these
numbers. Similarly, do this for each of
the square that you're encountering. If
at any instance you see that a number
was already present in your set, that
means this sudoku is not valid. If you
have iterated over entire elements and
find that okay, I'm not finding any
duplicates, then this sudoku is valid.
For example, try to notice what will
happen when I'm going over this row. So
for a row I'm going to take up this
hash. I start adding the elements. I add
a one here. Then I add a two then five.
Then three. And then what do I see? I
see a two again. Two is already present.
So immediately this sudoku is not valid
at all. Also if you notice closely we
have multiple eights in the same column.
So this sudoku is not valid with
multiple causes. But what did we do? In
just a single iteration, we were able to
verify if this sudoku is valid or not.
So what are we doing over here? How are
we identifying if you can apply the
hashmap or a hash fit pattern?
Basically, you should be asking yourself
some different kind of questions. Go
over the problem statement and try to
think about a solution. Try to think how
do you want to scan your elements? And
if some of these thoughts come to your
mind, for example, you have to find
duplicates, that is a very good
indicator you would need a hash fet
because in constant time you can
determine if a number has been
duplicated or not. Similarly, you might
want to count frequencies. So you are
given a string and you want to know how
many times a character is appearing.
Once again, you need a hashmap because
you can immediately pinpoint if the
number is present or not and then what
is the frequency. So what are we doing?
We are trying to track the state of a
particular element that have I
encountered this before and what was it
current state? It could be frequency. It
could just be the existence also. I hope
this is now giving you an idea where you
can apply this pattern. Let us continue
to solve more problems and you are going
to see how fast the process is. For
example, I have this problem over here
zero stripping. The problem says that
you are given a matrix like this. If you
see a zero anywhere, then this entire
column and the entire row they should
all get converted to zeros. That is the
desired output. If you check over here,
all of these elements have converted to
zero. And for this particular zero, both
the rows and columns have converted to
zero. When you solve this problem, you
cannot just start iterating and then as
soon as you see a zero, you cannot mark
all of these elements as zero because
you have to travel further also. And if
you do this then all of these columns
will start getting to mark zero. But
that is not what we desire. So somehow
you need to remember that okay I need to
make this column as zero and make this
row as zero. So once again you got your
hint. What you will do is you will make
a row hashet and you will make a column
hash set. In your row hashet you write
down which rows you want to make zero.
So I want to make row one as zero and I
want to make row three as zero. Which
columns I want to make zero. I want to
make column 1 as zero and column four as
zero. Now what you can do you have
iterated over every element. Just look
at these particular rows and columns and
marked them as zero. That's it. Once
again with just one scan you were able
to arrive at your solution.
This next problem is one which I really
like. You are given this array and you
have to tell me the longest chain of
consecutive integers that you can find.
So if you notice you can find one chain
1 2 and three. You cannot find a four.
So you can stop. Similarly you can also
find 5 6 7 8. This is also a chain. This
is longer for four elements. So over
here this is the answer. But you may ask
okay how can I apply a hash set or a
hashmap over here. While scanning
through the array, you need to somehow
remember that have I seen a smaller
element than this. Try to think if I am
looking at the element one. If in my
array I had a zero also that means zero
would be the starting point of a chain.
Correct? If I cannot find a element
smaller than one, it means this is the
starting point of probably a new chain.
Correct? So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take up a hash fit and then I
add up all of my numbers.
Now what you can do start off with the
first element. You need to look for a
zero. Can you find a zero in this set?
No. It means this is probably the
starting of a new sequence. And this
lookup happened immediately. You don't
have to waste time. So now what you can
do? You can look for two. And do you
find a two? Yes. What is the next
element that you have to look for? You
need to look for three. You can find a
three also. Can you find a four in here?
No. It means I found one of the length
as 1 2 and 3. This is my one chain that
I found. Now you move ahead and you get
the element six. Either this element six
will start a new chain or it will be a
part of some other longer chain. To be a
part of other longer chain you must have
five in your array also correct. So you
will look for five. Can you find it?
Yes. It simply means that six is not the
starting point. So I'm not going to do
any more iterations with it. I will just
skip this number because this isn't
starting a new chain. Go to two. Can you
find a one over here? Yes. It means two
is also not starting a new chain. Look
at the next element. Can you find a four
in your set? No. It means five is the
start of a new chain. So I need to find
out how big my chain is. So with five,
I'm going to look up six. Then I'm going
to look up seven. Then I look up eight.
Can I find a nine? No. So I can stop
over here. And what did I find? I found
5 6 7 8. This is another chain that I
found and it length is four. This is
longer. Correct. Now move ahead. For
eight, can you find seven? Yes. So,
don't do anything. For seven, can you
find a six? Yes. Don't do anything. For
10, can you find a nine? No. But you
can't find 11 either. For three, can you
find a two? Yes. So, you don't have to
do anything. So, what did we just do? We
did one scan to add all of the numbers
to our set. And in the other scan, we
were able to easily determine, hey, what
is my longest chain that I can found? So
once again we are just taking up order
of n extra space to find all of these
efficient solutions.
What about hash sets now and what about
strings? Valid anagram is a perfect
example how you can use them. What are
anagrams? Anagrams are simply two
strings where all of its characters are
just rearranged. They are the same
characters and the same frequencies. So
how can you use a hash effect? I have my
first string over here. just iterate
over each of the character and add them
to your hash set. So when you add all of
these characters, you get their
frequencies as well. A is one, D is 1, M
is 1, I is 1, R appears two times, and E
appears just one time. Notice that I can
do all of these lookups in just order of
one time. So I will just increment their
frequencies. Next, what you're going to
do? take up the second string and
iterate over each of the character. For
each of the character, you will do
immediate lookups with order of one time
and eventually you are going to reduce
the frequency of each of the character
that you're encountering.
At the very end, if all of these
frequencies have become zero, it means
the frequencies match and the characters
match. So, this two strings are
anagrams. But if any of the character
did not match or if you had an extra
character, for example, there was an X
over here, you will try to look up this
X in here. You can't find it. So you can
simply return a false. This makes life
so much simpler. Correct? And based upon
a similar idea, you can solve multiple
other problems also. For example,
contains duplicates. You are given a
string and you have to find out if it
has duplicates or not. just add them to
a set and if you encounter it again, you
have a duplicate. Intersection of two
arrays. You want to find out if these
arrays have an intersection point. Just
take up all of the elements of the first
array and add it to a set. Then take up
the second array and iterate over each
of the elements one by one. As soon as
you find something that is already
present in your hashet, that is the
intersection point. Similarly, you can
have one more example. the first unique
character in a string. So let us say you
have a string like a b c ab. What do you
do? Add all of these characters to a
hash set and store their frequencies.
The first character that you see that
has a frequency of one, that is your
answer. We just solved so many problems,
right? And this is the power of hash
fetss and hashmaps. Basically, you are
storing some kind of an extra state. You
are not just storing an element just
like an array. You are also containing
the information that this element
appears only once or has this appeared
earlier also. Similarly, it gives you
order of one lookup time and that is a
very essential feature. It just takes
constant time to query the set and
determine if it is present or not.
Similarly, it keeps your logic clean and
as you know it also reduces the time
complexity. You went from order of n
square time to mostly order of n time
and that is because you are reusing some
of the information. You avoided an extra
loop to look up that information and you
use your hash set. But always keep in
mind that using a hash set or a hashmap
can take up extra space. So you might
want to use it with caution. But it is
good in scenarios where you have a
constant sample size. For example, you
are dealing with the characters of
English alphabet. You know that there
can be a maximum of 26 characters. So
you are not taking up order of n space
but you are only taking up constant
space. So the space complexity actually
turns out to be order of one rather than
order of n. So these are some of the
examples where a hash set and a hashmap
can actually make your life very very
simple. Just tell me in the comment
section below where all have you used
this particular pattern and this will
really become a very good collection for
all of these such kind of problems. I
would be happy to discuss and contribute
to the collection as well. As a
reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated and I can make more such
videos. Also, now you can schedule a
one-to-one session with me to have a
direct interaction and solve any sort of
doubts. A huge shout out to all of the
members who support my channel. You guys
really keep me going and as a member,
you do get prior to reply to your
comments and early access to new videos
as well. Stay tuned for my upcoming
video. Until then, see youa.